Doug Cole fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Doug Cole fonds
1947 - 1995
F-35
Q100144791
1.13 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Cole, Doug
Dr. Douglas Cole was a Professor of History at Simon Fraser University from 1966 to 1997. His teaching and research interests centred on Canada: specifically, on the history of Canadian art, anthropology, and Indian-White relations. He was an active member of the university community, serving on a number of committees and as president of the Faculty Association from 1986 to 1988.
Douglas Lowell Cole was born in Mason City, Washington on December 9, 1938. In 1960, he received a Bachelor of Arts degree in history from Whitman College in Walla Walla, Washington.
Cole went on to complete his masters degree at George Washington University in Washington, DC in 1962 and then completed his Ph.D. at the University of Washington in 1968. Both his post-graduate degree theses focused on topics relevant to Canadian history. His MA thesis, "The United States and Canadian Diplomatic Independence, 1918-1926," and his Ph.D. thesis "John S. Ewart and the Canadian Nation," prepared him to accept a position teaching topics in Canadian history at Simon Fraser University.
During his career, Dr. Cole wrote numerous scholarly articles and books. In 1977, he co-wrote From Desolation to Splendour, a history of the changing perceptions of BC's landscape. Other books include Phillips in Print: The Selected Writing of Walter Phillips on Canadian Nature and Art (co-authored with M. Tippett), Captured Heritage, and An Iron Hand Upon the People (co-authored with Ira Chaikin). He has also contributed to BC Studies, Journal of Canadian Studies, Canadian Review of Nationalism, Canadian Historical Review, and others.
Dr. Cole was also the recipient of a number of awards, citations and honours. He was a finalist for the Harold Adams Innis Prize for best work in English in Social Sciences for An Iron Hand Upon the People. He was also awarded a Regional History Award from the Canadian Historical Association in 1987, the Molson Research Prize in 1986, and the Eaton Award for the best British Columbia book in 1978. Dr. Cole was also granted a University Research Professorship in 1990.
Dr. Cole passed away August 18, 1997.
published
Full
Published
Title of fonds based on its provenance.
Fonds consists of records reflecting the academic and personal life of Douglas Cole. The correspondence series consists primarily of the personal views of Dr. Cole on matters of historical scholarship, university affairs and his own career as a professor. A few letters were made or received by Dr. Cole in his capacity as a University employee performing his official duties –– for example, marking students' work and providing reference letters. Fonds also includes some unpublished articles, conference papers, research notes and lectures.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Department of History; Exploration, discovery and travel; First nations
The Douglas Cole fonds was donated to the SFU Archives in 1998 by Christine Mullins, the wife of Douglas Cole.
No further accruals are expected.
Correspondence series contains some documents that must be restricted in accordance with provincial Freedom of Information / Protection of Privacy legislation. These documents contain information relating to the employment and educational history of third parties such as students. Please see the archivist for further details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Correspondence, 1964 - 1995; F-35-1; 96 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of correspondence created and received by Dr. Douglas Cole in both his personal and professional life. Includes records that reflect his teaching and research interests, and his involvement in various university committees and professional offices. Also includes correspondence relating to awards, honours, and citations, research funding and publication of work.
  - General correspondence, 1964 - 1995; F-35-1-1; 92 cm of textual records
    - Correspondence, 1964 - 1966; F-35-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
      Textual records
      Restricted in whole
    - Correspondence - jobs, 1965 - 1970; F-35-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence - dissertation, 1965 - 1972; F-35-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence - Sampson, 1966 - 1969; F-35-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence, 1967; F-35-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence, 1968; F-35-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence, 1969; F-35-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence - Sampson, 1969 - 1973; F-35-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 35-1)
    - Correspondence, 1970; F-35-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence, 1971; F-35-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence, 1972; F-35-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1973; F-35-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1973; F-35-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence, 1973 - 1974; F-35-1-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence, 1974; F-35-1-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence, 1974 - 1975; F-35-1-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 35-2)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1975; F-35-1-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 35-3)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1975; F-35-1-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 35-3)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1975 - 1976; F-35-1-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 35-3)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1975 - 1976; F-35-1-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 35-3)
    - Correspondence, 1976 - 1977; F-35-1-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 35-3)
    - Correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-35-1-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 35-3)
    - Correspondence, 1978; F-35-1-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 35-4)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1978 - 1980; F-35-1-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 35-4)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1978 - 1980; F-35-1-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 35-4)
    - Correspondence, 1979; F-35-1-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 35-4)
    - Correspondence, 1980 - 1981; F-35-1-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 35-4)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1981; F-35-1-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 35-4)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1981; F-35-1-1-0-29 (Archival box - standard 35-5)
    - Correspondence, 1982 - 1983; F-35-1-1-0-30 (Archival box - standard 35-5)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1983; F-35-1-1-0-31 (Archival box - standard 35-5)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1983; F-35-1-1-0-32 (Archival box - standard 35-5)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1984; F-35-1-1-0-33 (Archival box - standard 35-5)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1984; F-35-1-1-0-34 (Archival box - standard 35-5)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1985; F-35-1-1-0-35 (Archival box - standard 35-6)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1985; F-35-1-1-0-36 (Archival box - standard 35-6)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1986; F-35-1-1-0-37 (Archival box - standard 35-6)
      Restricted in part
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1986; F-35-1-1-0-38 (Archival box - standard 35-6)
    - Correspondence, 1987; F-35-1-1-0-39 (Archival box - standard 35-6)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1988; F-35-1-1-0-40 (Archival box - standard 35-6)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1988; F-35-1-1-0-41 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1989; F-35-1-1-0-42 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1989; F-35-1-1-0-43 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1990; F-35-1-1-0-44 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1990; F-35-1-1-0-45 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence, 1990 - 1991; F-35-1-1-0-46 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence - 1/2, 1991; F-35-1-1-0-47 (Archival box - standard 35-7)
    - Correspondence - 2/2, 1991; F-35-1-1-0-48 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
    - Correspondence - Canadian Studies Program, 1994; F-35-1-1-0-49 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
    - Correspondence, 1995; F-35-1-1-0-50 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
  - Research correspondence, 1975 - 1991; F-35-1-2; 4 cm of textual records
    - Correspondence - The Beaver article on Paul Rand, 1975 - 1976; F-35-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
      Open
    - Correspondence - Bacstrom research, 1977 - 1980; F-35-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
    - Correspondence - Cunneah entry The Dictionary of Canadian Biography, 1979 - 1980; F-35-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
    - Correspondence - Ida Halpern, 1988 - 1991; F-35-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
- Unpublished articles, conference papers, research notes, and lectures, 1947 - 1995; F-35-2; 18 cm of textual records
  Series consists of unpublished work of Dr. Douglas Cole. Records reflect topics in Canadian and art history, such as anthropological exploration in the northwest, Indian policy, aesthetic views of the Canadian wilderness, and the like. Includes articles, conference papers, research notes and lectures.
  - Ewert lecture, 1968; F-35-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
  - Monash paper, 1968; F-35-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
  - Warren, H.J. - research notes for article in The Islander, 1973; F-35-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
  - Conference papers and lectures - 1/2, 1975 - 1995; F-35-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
  - Conference papers and lectures - 2/2, 1975 - 1995; F-35-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 35-8)
  - Wilderness Values and Canadian Taste, 1895-1930, 1976; F-35-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Bacstrom - research notes, 1977 - 1980; F-35-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Paul Rand - exhibit catalogue, 1979; F-35-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Conference papers, 1981; F-35-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Indians and WW II, 1989 - 1990; F-35-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Desperately Seeking Absolution: A Response, 1995; F-35-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Conference papers, F-35-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - National Gallery Controversy - notes for article (unpublished), F-35-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Notes for unpublished article - Frederick Whymper, F-35-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Articles written by or about Ida Halpern, 1952 - 1986; F-35-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Articles written by or about Ida Halpern, 1955 - 1957; F-35-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Articles written by or about Ida Halpern, 1947 - 1987; F-35-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 35-9)
  - Photographs of George and Ida Halpern, F-35-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 35-9)